A Guide to the Henkel-Miller Family Papers, 1793-1910
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Henkel-Miller Family Papers 1793-1910
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
14434
606 items contained in 5 Hollinger boxes, 2.5 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no Restrictions
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased from the Museum of Early Southern Decorative Arts, Winston-Salem, North Carolina, on November 17, 2008.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Henkel family of New Market, Virginia, operated the Henkel printing press which became the most important bilingual printing establishment for German Lutherans in the states of Virginia, Tennessee, and North Carolina during the nineteenth century. Paul Henkel (1754-1825) was an itinerate Lutheran preacher involved with various synods in Ohio, Pennsylvania, Tennessee, Maryland and North Carolina. Solomon David Henkel (1777-1847), Paul's son, was a physician, teacher and head of the Henkel Press along with his brother, Ambrose (1786-1870). Andrew Henkel (1790-1870), was also the son of Paul Henkel as well as an itinerate preacher and educator. Samuel G. Henkel (1807-1863), was the son of Solomon and continued running the press after his father's death.
For more information concerning the contributions of the Henkel family to the printing of religious works and preaching in the Lutheran Church, consult Klaus Wust's Guide to the Henkel Family Papers and Christopher L. Dolmetsch's book, The German Press of the Shenandoah Valley.
Scope and Content
This collection contains 606 items contained in 5 Hollinger boxes (2.5 linear feet) concerning the Henkel Family of Shenandoah and the operation of the Henkel Press in New Market, Virginia. The dates of the materials range from 1793-1910, with the bulk of the material coming from the first half of the nineteenth century.
The journals of Paul Henkel give a history of his travels and family as well as the history of the Shenandoah Valley. The journals also are a depiction of parts of Pennsylvania, Maryland, the Carolinas, Tennessee and Ohio that interacted with the Shenandoah Valley. Many of these journals along with Paul Henkel's correspondence were used by Dr. William J. Finck to write the "Chronological Life of Paul Henkel" (MSS 2827).
Solomon D. Henkel is the chief recipient of the correspondence as he, along with his brother, Ambrose, is the head of the press. He also served as the postmaster of New Market, physician and educator. The correspondence covers a variety of subjects concerning Solomon's multiple expertise. He does not only receive letters concerning his own business, but also in regard to the business of others due to his position as postmaster. The collection is invaluable as a source of information on the Henkel Family, the starting and operation of the press, the decline of German as a prominent language in the Shenandoah Valley, and the activities of Lutheran Preachers during this period. Many of the Henkels' business contacts were also personal friends so the letters include aspects of daily life as well as the logistical matters of the business.
Much of the later material in the collection is the correspondence, both to and from, Samuel G. Henkel, Solomon's son. Samuel's memorandum books are also a tremendous source of logistical information especially as it pertains to the history of commercial imports to the Winchester Millers and the New Market Henkels from New York, Philadelphia, Baltimore and Alexandria. Information includes names of merchants, locals, printing, medicines, books, etc.
Some items of interest are the correspondence of John Barnett (1814-1819) which concerns a variety of subjects, including the treatment of maladies, crop prices and book sales; a series of letters from the War of 1812, including a discussion of the moral implications of military service, conditions at Camp Crossroads and the defense of Baltimore particularly the battle of North Point and the bombardment of Ft. McHenry where the writer, William Warner, noted "naught could be seen but the light of Rockets and the bursting of Bombs thrown from their shipping at our fort...."; a letter from Jacob Woltz of February 9, 1811 concerning retribution against slaves that killed their masters; the correspondence of Warner and Schaeffer from Baltimore, March 26, 1813, who must take into account the positions of British troops when shipping goods to New Market. The two letters of Gideon Jones from November 1818 describe relations with the Cherokees of Georgia, the Secret Green Corn Dance, and the African slaves of the Native Americans.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in three series topically, alphabetically and chronologically. The manuscripts for publication are organized alphabetically by title. Series I is correspondence of the Henkel Press, Series II is the correspondence of the Henkel Family and other items of historical importance, and Series III is manuscripts intended for publication. Boxes 1 and 2 contain correspondence, primarily letters addressed to Solomon or Ambrose Henkel or to the Henkel Press in general. Boxes 3 and 4 contain other historical resources on the Henkel Press including historical notes by a later hand and the journals and memoranda books of the Henkels. Box 5 contains the remainder of the journals and memorandum books as well as manuscripts for items that might have been meant for publication.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence of the Henkel Press
  - 1805-1811 Henkel Press Correspondence -General (16 items). Correspondence both in English and German. Correspondents include: John Stock, Samuel Strickler, Hannah Lee, Abraham Lauck, Samuel Nicholson, Solomon Perrin, J. Herschberger, Starck and Lange, George Hudson, Joseph Graff, William Chambers, Daniel West, Jacob D. Dietrich, Bryan Hampson, and Simon Yager. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - 1812-1815 Henkel Press Correspondence -General (22 items). Correspondence both in English and German. Correspondents include: Daniel West, Charles B. Rhoades, W.F. Thornton, Matthias Kin, Christian Friedrich Schaaf, David Irving, John Blessing, Anthony Weier, David Crawford, Webster Lewis, Peter Eckle (Eckel), George Bourne, Littleberry Purty, John Brown, John B. Groves (Grovis), Slingluff and Fahnestock, A.D. Carden, and George Brittan. Letter of note: June 8, 1815, Matthias Kin to Solomon Henkel: death of Heinrich Muhlenburgh (Muhlenberg) (Box-folder 1:2)
  - 1816-1818 Henkel Press Correspondence -General (19 items). Correspondence both in English and German. Correspondents include: Abel Gibbons, Matthias Sommer, Samuel Harshaw, Jacob Stiegel, Jacob Binckle (Bueklü), Henry Printz, William Marye, Gideon Bottler, John Hoke, Abraham Fravel, Bryan Hampson, John Walker Jr., Peachy Hampson (Harrison), Michael Meyerhoeffer, Margret (Margaretha) Fisher, and Gideon L. Jones. (Box-folder 1:3)
  - 1819-1821 Henkel Press Correspondence -General (22 items). Correspondence both in English and German. Correspondents include: R.C.P. Barton, Samuel Brown, G. McGlassin (McGlassen), Zachariah Shugart, Linn Banks, Henry Fry, Abraham Fravel, John Koontz, B.L. Bogan, J.H. Smoot, William Widdifield, B. Allen, Jacob Garst, Daniel Smith, Edward Almond, William F. Dinninger, Joseph Funk, Stephen North, and H. Swann. (Box-folder 1:4)
  - 1822-1825, n.d. Henkel Press Correspondence-General (11 items) Correspondence both in English and German. Correspondents include: Sam H. Davis, Jacob Pinkey, David Schweitzer, Kaspar Reinardt (Keinack), Martin Walter, David Ruffner, Pastor Schullehrer, G.H. Riemenschneider. (Box-folder 1:5)
  - 1814-1819 John Barnett to Solomon Henkel (5 items). John Barnett is a resident of Rockbridge County, Virginia. He writes chiefly about health issues of his own and the people in the vicinity. November 12, 1814: two sons in the service, request some high quality paper; June 4, 1816: no colic for several months, crop prices, lots of people dying of consumption; June 15, 1816: just had the severest spell of colic, reference to mail not getting through; December 8, 1816: had a severe spell of colic about two weeks ago, hurt leg, boils on other leg, received a hymn book; August 29, 1819: unwell, "sore through the whole system" and refers an ailing Eliza McKnight to Solomon. Letters in English. (Box-folder 1:6)
  - 1804-1820 John Bottler to Solomon Henkel (2 items). Business, primarily pharmaceuticals. Letters in English and German. (Box-folder 1:7)
  - 1818-1820 Augustus Bournier to Solomon Henkel (5 items). February 25, 1819: Bournier's father is engaging him to go to France and Bournier would like to spend his last months in America near Solomon in New Market; May 3, 1819: News of the success of the school and the regular visits of a Lutheran preacher; April 29, 1820: Bournier has spoken with the French Ambassador, Hyde de Neuville, and will set off for France, leaves for Annapolis the following day. Letters in English. (Box-folder 1:8)
  - 1811-1820 John Buckius to Solomon Henkel (8 items). John Buckius (Buckus) was a coppersmith from New Market working in Canton, Stark County, Ohio. Letters in English and German. (Box-folder 1:9)
  - 1819-1821 William Davison (Davidson) to Solomon Henkel (3 items). Coppersmith in Winchester, Virginia. October 7, 1821: concerns a request made by Solomon, acknowledges a packet received. Letters in English. (Box-folder 1:10)
  - 1817-1820 Ananias Davisson (Davidson) to Solomon Henkel (9 items) Harrisonburg, Virginia. Singing school teacher and publisher. Correspondence chiefly concerns the publishing of books for use in his school, especially the famous "Kentucky Harmony." October 25, 1817: 200 copies sent to Solomon, the whole 1000 were not sent because Mrs. [Mortinen?] failed to get them folded; October 29, 1817: book business, specifications, books received; November 3, 1817: 1000 books sent to Solomon along with blank paper, wants leather bound, wrote a small treatise on the nature of music; November 13, 1817: request for one dozen books; November 19, 1817; printing business, pamphlets; November 26, 1817: Angry letter, not getting books on time because Ambrose will not do anything until his wife is restored to health; December 11, 1817: Ambrose finishing some full bound books, request to add names on "back or cover", relays a book order from Mr. H.D. Carden; November 12, 1818: request to get a copy of book binding prices in Baltimore; November 15, 1820: money business. Letters in English. (Box-folder 1:11)
  - 1812-1814 Heinrich Diefenbach to Solomon Henkel (2 items). Lutheran minister and fraktur artist. Greenwich Township, Bercks (Berks) County, Pennsylvania. Letters in German. (Box-folder 1:12)
  - 1812-1843 Adolph Flodoardo to Solomon Henkel (3 items). Resident of New Market. Correspondence chiefly concerns printing orders and German medicine. Letters in German. (Box-folder 1:13)
  - 1813-1816 Jonathan Foster to Solomon Henkel (6 items). Proprietor of the Republican Constellation Establishment, Winchester, Virginia. Letters all concern subscriptions. Letters in English. (Box-folder 1:14)
  - 1801-1819 John Gruber to Solomon Henkel (18 items). John Gruber and D. May, printers in Hagerstown, Maryland, concern the formation of the Henkel Press and often request to exchange some of their product for books from Henkel Press. November 9, 1801: twelve dozen calendars sent to Solomon, newspapers, invoices, accounts of various people; July 12, 1802: regrets that he cannot assemble the money soon enough; July 27, 1802: Solomon is having difficulty with subscribers to the Westliche Correspondenz, a newspaper from Hagerstown; September 28, 1802: twelve dozen calendars and can get more from Baltimore; May 23, 1803: reference to Jacob Ohlinger, selling of calendars and books, subscriptions; September 16, 1803: twelve dozen calendars at 6/10 Maryland currency per dozen; July 9, 1804: Michael Zirkle, Abraham Hiertand, Caspar Hoffer, and other news concerning acquaintances; July 24, 1804: writing in haste, the almanac is finished in part; December 23, 1804: sent eight dozen calendars for 1805 and one half dozen books, explanation of shipping; September 16, 1805: has sent eight dozen calendars, John Beckley, did not want this opportunity to pass by; October 27, 1805: bill for German and English almanacs, will send news with the next books and pamphlets, has no time now; January 20, 1806: has printed 500 confessionals; February 24, 1806, calendars, printing, newspapers; March 17, 1806: John Bock, printing business, ABC books; July 14, 1806: hears that Solomon wants to start a printing press in New Market, refers him to Mr. Zentler, some information regarding printing (translation on insert); August 18, 1806: David Harry, Isaac Reidenaur, sending calendars and the shipping of items; November 14, 1817: copyright and prices; April 26, 1819: wants to exchange extra English Heidelberg catechisms in loose sheets for German spelling books, no bindery in Hagerstown. Letters in English and German. (Box-folder 1:15)
  - 1806-1814 J.H.C. Helmuth to Solomon Henkel (5 items) Preacher from Philadelphia who makes use of the books the Henkels print. Letters in German. (Box-folder 1:16)
  - 1799-1812, n.d. David Jackson and his wife, Susan Jackson, to Solomon Henkel (13 items) Jackson and Betton is a druggist firm in Philadelphia. Correspondence is chiefly business and invoices with some personal topics. Letters of note: December 31, 1799: discusses the advanced prices due to the war in Europe; September 21, 1801: announces the death of David Jackson (Sr.) and the continuance of business; April 12, 1803: announces a separation of a partnership in Germantown; July 25, 1803: David Jackson (Jr.) has taken on the family business. Letters in English. (Box-folder 1:17)
  - 1811-1822 Henry Keerl and Sons to Solomon Henkel (8 items). Druggist in Baltimore. Correspondence is chiefly business with very little personal content. Letters in English. (Box-folder 1:18)
  - 1811-1812 William Kreps to Solomon Henkel (3 items). Post master of Hagerstown. March 30, 1811: account of Mr. Pennybaker; September 14, 1811: has written Mr. Pennybaker concerning his debt, but has not received and answer; Letters in English and German. (Box-folder 1:19)
  - 1816-1822 Jacob Lawton-Solomon Henkel (3 items). Father of a student of Solomon's buys land in Arkansas. He inquires as to the health and whereabouts of his family and relates information on 19th century Arkansas. May 11, 1816: requests that Solomon tell his son to write. Letters in English. (Box-folder 1:20)
  - 1810 William Marshall to Ambrose Henkel (2 items). Informs Henkel of the need for a printed title page. August 6, 1810: requests a title page printed according to law so that a copyright can be made. Letters in English. (Box-folder 1:21)
  - 1812-1813 F.A. Mayo to Solomon Henkel (3 items). Bookseller from Staunton wishes to purchase or exchange English and German books of various sorts with the Henkel Press. January 29, 1812: request for a small quantity of German books that he can sell, he would be happy to send something as soon as possible; April 21, 1813: request for more writing paper; June 1, 1813: has books of writing paper, needs to buy more from Solomon; Letters in English and German. (Box-folder 1:22)
  - 1809 October 18 Solomon Meyer, Washington City, to Solomon Henkel (1 item). Meyer was the printer of The York Gazette. Writes concerning his plan to set up a new printing business in Washington for his sons while he continues to run a "Congress boarding house"; Letter in English (Box-folder 1:22a)
  - 1800-1821 Abraham Miller to Solomon Henkel (21 items). Most letters are from Winchester, Virginia. The Millers were frequent suppliers to the Henkel Press and to Solomon Henkel as a physician. Some letters are from business trips to Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. Content concerns business, medical and personal topics. August 13, 1800: Advises Solomon on buying a house; March 15, 1802: will be visiting March 29 to see a child with a harelip; April 6, 1802: follow-up on the child's lip; July 6, 1802: Response to Solomon who did not get all the medicine he ordered; December 27, 1803: Abraham's father died; February 26, 1805: Mother has a relapse of rheumatism in her arm; November 18, 1805: Business in Stanton (Staunton); April 2, 1806: plans to visit; May 20, 1808: Miss Kurtz's death; October 30, 1808: Going to New York and asks if Solomon needs anything from there. Letters in English. (Box-folder 1:23)
  - 1819, 1844 Frederick (Friedrich) and Louis Miller to Henkel Press (3 items). Hagerstown, Maryland and Winchester, Virginia. Matters of business and health. Letters in English. (Box-folder 1:24)
  - 1803-1823, n.d. Godfrey (Gottfried) Miller to Solomon Henkel (39 items). Winchester, Virginia. Majority of content concerns the Miller's business which sold a variety of items and was closely affiliated with the Red Bud Paper Mill. December 7, 1803: father is very sick; August 23, 1808: family matters; November 28, 1808: offers Solomon the services of a house servant; June 5, 1809: family news, Solomon should visit in the Summer; January 15, 1811: concerning a house table "Haus Dafel" sent by Solomon that the Millers will put in their parlor; July 8, 1811: paid Ambrose $50; March 13, 1812: McNester died, whole city is grieving; September 12, 1812: hopes for a visit in the Fall; July 23, 1813: Abraham returned on Tuesday the 20th; July 31, 1813: Abraham Miller is on his way to Philadelphia; October 12, 1814: Lewis Sherry is looking to settle in New Market; March 1, 1815: German almanacs are on their way to Solomon from Mr. Murdock's bookstore; August 9, 1815: honey and family business; January 20, 1816: books sent, information on counterfeit bills; May 18, 1816: reference to Adam Kurtz and his wife, Silas and Abraham in Philadelphia: December 31, 1816: books and a coffee mill; January 30, 1817: business and family; April 5, 1818: Godfrey send a number encyclopedia, request for two dozen English catechisms, one dozen German ABC books, and some coffee; January 7, 1819: business concerning books and medicine; January 27, 1819: trouble finding writing paper; February 6, 1819: business; March 4, 1819: goods sent to Solomon; August 5, 1819: handmade gifts sent, prospect of coming to New Market; August 19, 1821: request for three dozen English catechisms, Solomon's "boys" are in Winchester; August 16, 1823: Books received; July 9, 18 [?]: has bought oil that he is willing to sell. Letters in German and English. (Box-folder 1:25)
  - 1801-1813 John (Johannes) Miller to Solomon Henkel (26 items). Winchester and Norfolk, Virginia. Business and personal correspondence. The Millers in Winchester were frequent suppliers to the Henkel Press and to Solomon Henkel as a physician. January 13, 1801: singing schools in New Market, books; January 20, 1801: copies sent; February 18, 1801: Medicines sent to John Groves in New Town; June 5, 1801: invoice and business news; November 17, 1801: returned from Baltimore, bought some goods, indigo, etc.; December 4, 1801: indigo, will no longer deal with Jackson and Betton (prices too high), will try Charles Marshall and Son; January 12, 1802: business proposition (diversification); February 2, 1802: shipping mistake; December 27, 1802: prices for advertising, Helena with the measles; June 22, 1807: Family and friends, travelling and visiting; January 12, 1808: business with a shoemaker in New Market; December 27, 1808: drug prices on the rise; June 6, 1809: received the potash but it was soft and had to dry out; July 18, 1809: business, hopes to visit; August 5, 1809: Sends money that he got from Abraham; August 15, 1809: Mother, wife and child arrived safely; November 21, 180[9]: Death of Gotlob Miller (Uncle); April 22, 1811: business and the quality of Daniel Hoof; July 20, 1812: invoice and business; September 22, 1813: writing from Norfolk, seeks medical advice; October 2, 1813: writing from Norfolk, back in perfect health, British have taken one of the vessels from Baltimore. Letters in English and German. (Box-folder 2:1)
  - 1814-1823, 1845 John Miller to Solomon Henkel-includes John Bell to Solomon Henkel announcing the death of John Miller (23 items). All letters from Winchester except April 2, 1821, which is from Frederick Lawn, Maryland. Some letters are signed J & A Miller, presumably meaning John and Abraham. June 27, 1814: John Lutz from Georgetown on his way to Kentucky, medical business; July 4, 1814: goods and medicines; August 1, 1814: fever, Helena and Maryann begin school with Mr. Curlet; October 17, 1814: Helena in Winchester, Abraham in Philadelphia; October 29, 1814: medicine has not yet arrived, nor has Abraham from Philadelphia; January 8, 1815: Miller's father-in-law died on November 9 (74 years old), wife's mother also died, Adam Kurtz's wife died in childbirth, missed Helena; April 18, 1817: wants Helena to visit, Mr. Hill will take female scholars, Abraham in Philadelphia; October 15, 1817: Peter is very sick; October 28, 1817: Peter is well again, store business; December 1, 1817: Aunt Kurtz died, will send Helena a jar of preserves; December 13, 1817: business, various goods; May 2, 1818: request to reserve a pair of rabbits for the boys; September 5, 1820: coming to New Market, bringing his sister, Rebecca, and his daughter, Maryann: October 3, 1820: arrived safely home, Adam Bowers died last Saturday night; December 2, 1820: business; April 2, 1821: business concerning a box of type; January 23, 1822: Peter's wife died last Saturday night; November 21, 1823: response to the news of Helena's death. Letters in English. (Box-folder 2:2)
  - 1810-1820 Red Bud Paper Mill (26 items). Frederick County, Maryland. Correspondence chiefly concerns the supply of paper to the Henkel Press. Correspondents include: John Martin, Ann Martin, Rebecca Gildtz, John Geisinger (Guisinger), John Carter, and Smith and Barton. Some letters contain the Red Bud Paper Mill watermark. Letters in English. (Box-folder 2:3)
  - 1801-1814 Heinrich Muhlenberg to Solomon Henkel (7 items). Lancaster, Pennsylvania. January 21, 1802: responds to Solomon Henkel's news about the religious revival in Carolina, some pharmaceutical matters; July 13, 1802: business, plants and other goods; August 18, 1805 short note on business, books and a horse doctor; January 6, 1806: reference to the Synod, books and business with Great Britain; June 23, 1808: reference to the Synod, some opinions on what a missionary should do; July 25, 1814: business both in America and abroad. Letters in German. (Box-folder 2:4)
  - 1809-1812, n.d. Samuel Saur (Sower, Sauer) to Solomon Henkel (8 items). Baltimore, Maryland. Concerns the selling of printing type to the Henkel Press. August 1, 1812 is from Ambrose Henkel, New Market, Virginia, to Saur. February 20, 1809: type sent to Alexandria; March 23, 1809: business with Bryan Hampson in Alexandria; June 12, 1811: received the catechism, but a letter must have fallen out; August 9, 1811: has directed their italic type to B. Harrison in Alexandria; August 1, 1812: Ambrose cannot go to Baltimore as he is going to the southern states, request for type; September 7, 1812: shipped two boxes of type for the Henkels to B. Harrison in Alexandria; December 22, 1812: settlement of accounts. Letters in German and English. (Box-folder 2:5)
  - 1854 Charles Shaeffer to Henkel Press (12 items). Easton, Pennsylvania. Concerns the editing and proofreading of Henkel Press texts, especially the translation of the Concordien Buch (Book of Concord). Letters in English. (Box-folder 2:6)